Today's דף Daf is י"ח Yud-Chet and we pick up in the
middle of י"ז עמוד
ב'.
Yud-Zayin Amud
Bet. We have just seen that this debate was told over differently
between נהרדעא Neharde'a and סורא. Sura.
In סורא, Sura, רב'ס ישיבה, Rav's Yeshiva, the students were saying that
both רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel make a difference, make a distinction
between whether the פסול סכך pasul schach is on the side or
in the middle. On the side, it's ארבע אמות arba amot to
be a problem because otherwise you would bend the wall, דופן עקומה.
dofen akumah. In the middle, it is ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim that
separates the two halves of the סכך. schach. As we discussed with
תוספות, Tosafot, it doesn't invalidate the whole סוכה sukkah in one fell
swoop; what it does is it cuts the סכך schach in half
and therefore sometimes you'll be left with two פסול סוכות, pasul sukkot,
sometimes you'll be left with one כשר kasher and one פסול, pasul,
but ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim create the problem to divide the סכך.
schach.
That's if it's in the middle. This is in opposition to the
position of רבה, Rabba, and רבה Rabba says even in the middle
it's ארבע אמות, arba amot, and that's רבה'ס Rabba's position.
But again, according to in נהרדעא, Neharde'a, שמואל'ס ישיבה, Shmuel's Yeshiva, they
said actually this was a debate between רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
שמואל Shmuel was the one who made the difference between on the
side and in the middle: ארבע אמות arba amot on the side,
bend the wall, middle ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim creates a separate space,
divides it by a different space and divides the סכך schach into
two.
That's שמואל'ס Shmuel's position. And רב Rav says whether the middle, whether
the side, ארבע אמות. arba amot. And as we have seen in
one or two other places in this מסכת, Masechet, here too, although
we normally rule like רב, Rav, we are going to rule like
שמואל. Shmuel. I don't think anybody ever imagined that they could have
up to ארבע אמות arba amot of פסול סכך pasul schach in
the middle of their סוכה. sukkah. So we actually do wind up
ruling like שמואל, Shmuel, which is quite fascinating, again, at least that's
according to the נהרדעא Neharde'a version where this is a debate between
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. According to the סורא Sura version, we're
ruling like the consensus opinion of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel who
make this distinction between on the side and in the middle.
Question: You said we have this פסול סכך pasul schach right down
the middle, you'd be left with a כשר kasher and a פסול
סוכה pasul sukkah or two פסול סוכות. pasul sukkot.
Why couldn't you
be left with two כשר kasher ones? If you had four walls,
that is absolutely correct.
The גמרא Gemara is always assuming a three-wall סוכה, sukkah, and you
are absolutely correct, if you had a four-wall סוכה, sukkah, right, and
you have your
כשר סכך kasher schach here, right, and your פסול סכך pasul schach
here and your כשר סכך kasher schach here, you're left with two
separate סוכות, sukkot, each one with three walls. You are absolutely correct.
The גמרא Gemara is just assuming a three-wall סוכה. sukkah. In a
four-wall סוכה, sukkah, it is divided into two separate כשר kasher ones
and then you just couldn't obviously
sit in the middle.
Okay. So now let's take a look, but now we're within the
סורא Sura version,
the נהרדעא Neharde'a version that this is a debate of רב Rav
and שמואל. Shmuel. Where exactly? We are, good question, about to tell
you. Where it says תנן, tnan, it is about twenty lines from
the bottom,
right by an asterisk. Okay, it says באמצע ארבע אמות. be'emtza arba
amot. Okay.
Can I make a public service announcement? Please. רבקה Rivka is home.
Oh good. But she's not receiving visitors yet. I just got a
text message from אברהם, Avraham, just so I didn't want to forget.
Thank you. Thank you. Actually, let's start four lines above that.
בנהרדעא מתנו. Binharde'a matnu. The line starts with מתנו. matnu. In נהרדעא,
Neharde'a, here was the version. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel, סכך באמצע פסול בארבעה. schach be'emtza pasul be'arba'ah.
In the middle, ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim is now what שמואל Shmuel
is saying. מן הצד פסול בארבע אמות. min hatzad pasul be'arba amot.
On the side, ארבע אמות. arba amot. ורב אמר, veRav amar, and
רב Rav says according to שמואל'ס ישיבה, Shmuel's Yeshiva, רב Rav disagrees,
בין מן הצד ובין באמצע בארבע אמות. bein min hatzad uvein be'emtza
be'arba amot.
It's always ארבע אמות. arba amot. תנן, Tnan, now as opposed to
yesterday where we tried to figure this out by logical arguments, here
we're going to try to use textual proofs to prove one side
or the other. תנן, Tnan, the משנה Mishnah says, now we're going
to revisit משניות Mishnayot that we saw before that we had sort
of been implicitly interpreting a little bit according to this debate, now
we're going to actually see how the variant interpretations based on which
side you adopt. תנן, Tnan, the משנה Mishnah says, נתן עליה נסר
שרחב ארבעה טפחים. natan aleha neser sherochav arba'ah tefachim.
If you put on the סוכה sukkah a plank that is ארבעה
טפחים arba'ah tefachim wide, כשרה, kesherah, it's כשר. kasher. Okay,
the סוכה sukkah remains כשר kasher even though the plank, this is
according to the position that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir or maybe they
say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that these
types of planks are פסול. pasul. But the משנה Mishnah is telling
you even though the plank is פסול, pasul, the סוכה sukkah remains
a כשר סוכה. kasher sukkah. So how does that work? בשלמא לרב
דאמר בין באמצע בין מן הצד בארבע אמות. bishlama leRav de'amar bein
be'emtza bein min hatzad be'arba amot.
So according to רב, Rav, it works just fine. He says that
פסול סכך, pasul schach, whether on the side or the middle, requires
ארבע אמות. arba amot. משום הכי כשרה, mishum hachi kesherah, so the
סוכה sukkah is כשר. kasher.
You wouldn't be able to sit under the פסול סכך pasul schach
once it's ארבעה טפחים, arba tefachim, it's significant, and that's if you
remember, that's what the משנה Mishnah said, ואין ישנים תחתיו, ve'ein yeshenim
tachtav, right,
the סוכה sukkah is כשר kasher but don't eat or sleep under
it, fine, don't. need or sleep under it, but it doesn't affect
the כשרות *kashrus* of the סוכה Sukkah *sukkah* because you need four
אמות amot, *amos*. Four טפחים tefachim *tefachim* won't affect the כשרות *kashrus*.
That works beautifully according to רב Rav. *Rav*. אלא לשמואל דאמר באמצע
be-emtza. בארבע *Ella l’Shmuel d’amar b’emtza b’arba*, but
שמואל *Shmuel* says that once it's in the middle, four טפחים tefachim
*tefachim* actually invalidates the סוכה Sukkah *sukkah*, cuts the סוכה Sukkah *sukkah*
in half. אמאי כשרה amai kesherah, *Amai keshera*? Why does the משנה
mishnah *Mishnah* say that the סוכה Sukkah, *sukkah* remains כשרה kesherah. *kosher*?
So גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, הכא במאי עסקינן *hacha b’mai askinan*, what
are we talking about? מן הצד min ha-tzad. *min hatzad*.
When the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* says you can put up a plank
and the סוכה Sukkah *sukkah* remains כשרה kesherah *kosher*, it doesn't mean
in the middle, it would mean when you put it up on
the side, which it never says in the משנה mishna *Mishnah*. The
משנה mishna *Mishnah* reads obviously much better according to רב *Rav*. משנה
*Mishnah* says a four טפחים tefachim, *tefachim* plank which is פסול pasul.
*pasul* does not invalidate the סוכה Sukkah. *sukkah*. רב *Rav* says perfect,
that's exactly what I've been saying all along. And שמואל *Shmuel* says
we're talking about a case where it is on the side and
it's because you are bending the wall. Okay, let's try again. תא
שמע *Ta shema*, okay, here we go again, and this is a
ברייתא braita: *braisa*, but again, you'll remember this was brought into the
discussion earlier with the whole issue of planks. שני סדינין מצטרפין *Shnei
sadinim mitztarfin*, two sheets can combine. If you have a sheet that's
I don't know three טפחים tefachim *tefachim* wide and another sheet that's
a טפח tefach. *tefach* wide, you know, they're both totally פסול סכך
pasul sechach *pasul sechach* and you put them next to each other,
then it's four טפחים tefachim *tefachim* of invalid סכך skhach. *sechach* or
four אמות amot. *amos* if that's what you need. But two sheets
combine to create enough invalid סכך skhach, *sechach*. שני נסרין אין מצטרפין
*Shnei nesarin ein mitztarfin*. Two planks do not combine. Why? Because this
is the opinion that planks are not really invalid סכך skhach. *sechach*,
so therefore they don't combine. Okay, or certainly planks less than four
טפחים tefachim *tefachim* are not invalid and therefore there's no problem. רבי
Rebbi, מאיר אומר נסרין כסדינין *Rabbi Meir omer nesarin k’sadinim*, רבי Rebbi,
מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, if you remember, who's the one that has the
issue with planks, says no, planks are just like a sheet and
therefore they would combine to give you enough פסול סכך pasul sechach.
*pasul sechach*. Now, how's this going to work? Well, we have to
figure out how big these planks are so we can understand, you
know, what how much you're combining them to create. So if you
remember that was debated before. Are we debating planks is the debate
of רבי Rebbi, מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* about planks between the size of three and four, or is
the debate with planks the size of four and larger? People vaguely
remember that debate? Okay, good, a few heads nodding. So let's try
the two approaches of this and see which ones work out. בשלמא
Bishlama להך לישנא דאמר רב *Bishlama l’hach lishna d’amar Rav*, now this
is interesting, since this we're discussing a רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel*
debate here, we're going to test it according to what רב *Rav*
said over there. So according to the approach that רב *Rav*
said, according to the approach that רב *Rav* said, בין באמצע be-emtza
בין מן הצד min ha-tzad. בארבע אמות be-arba amot, *bein b’emtza bein
min hatzad
b’arba amos*, so
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* isn't saying but is implicit is that
רב *Rav* said the debate of רבי Rebbi, יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* about planks is only by four טפחים tefachim
*tefachim* and larger planks. Okay, so here's the issue. You've got, right,
two planks,
you've got your two planks, and רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says מצטרפין *mitztarfin*, right, and רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says אין מצטרפין *ein mitztarfin*, okay,
to combine to the minimum size. Now, how big are these planks?
So this is the debate of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*, whether planks are a problem. If you'll remember, רב *Rav*
said they are debating planks that are the size of four טפחים
tefachim *tefachim* and bigger. Less than four טפחים tefachim *tefachim* even רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* doesn't have a problem. Okay, so the planks here
are four טפחים tefachim *tefachim* at least. So now what does רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* mean they combine? Why isn't one plank enough to
create a problem? You already have four טפחים tefachim *tefachim*. But we're
dealing according to רב *Rav* who says this is the debate. But
if the same רב *Rav* says that in the middle you need
four אמות amot *amos*, then we know what it means to combine:
combine enough planks so that you have four אמות amot *amos*. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is, let's take a look. בשלמא
להך לישנא *Bishlama l’hach lishna*, it's good according to that approach, דאמר
רב בין באמצע בין מן הצד min ha-tzad. בארבע אמות amot *d’amar
Rav bein b’emtza bein min hatzad b’arba amos*, that רב *Rav* said
the approach of סורא *Sura*, of excuse me of נהרדעא *Nehardea*, that
according to רב *Rav* in the middle also needs four אמות amot
*amos* to be a problem, מאי מצטרפין *mai mitztarfin*, so why would
you need to combine the planks since we're talking about four טפח
tefach, *tefach* planks? מצטרפין לארבע אמות amot, *mitztarfin l’arba amos*, you combine
so many planks that you have four אמות amot *amos* because you
need four אמות amot *amos* to invalidate the סוכה Sukkah *sukkah*. אלא
להך לישנא דאמר רב באמצע בארבע *Ella l’hach lishna d’amar Rav b’emtza
b’arba*, but according to the version in סורא *Sura* where רב *Rav*
says that even in the middle is four טפחים tefachim *tefachim* and
the same רב *Rav* says that we're discussing planks of four טפחים
tefachim. *tefachim*, according to that approach who needs to combine? One plank
invalidates the סוכה Sukkah *sukkah*. היכי דמי *Heichi dami*, what's the case?
אי דאית בהו ארבע *Ei d’is behu arba*, if it's four טפחים
tefachim *tefachim* wide, למה להו לצירופי *lama lehu l’tzerufei*, who needs to
combine? It itself invalidates. אי דלית בהו ארבע *Ei d’les behu arba*,
if it doesn't have four, קניא בעלמא נינהו *kanya b’alma ninhu*, it's
just a stick. According to רב *Rav* who himself says that they
don't debate less than four. Less than four everybody says it's just
a stick and doesn't even count as a plank. So גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, לעולם דאית בהו ארבע *Le'olam de'is behu arba*. Fine. They're
four טפחים tefachim *Tefachim* obviously they have to be, because according to
רב *Rav* that's what they're debating, רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* and רבי
מאיר *Rebbe Meir*. ומה מצטרפין *U'mai mitztarfin*, so why would you need
to combine them? מצטרפין לאו אהדדי אלא מן הצד min ha-tzad. *Mitztarfin
lav ahadadei ela min hatzad* because you're talking that the plank is
not in the middle. The plank is in the middle, then according
to this version of רב *Rav*, four טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* already invalidates
the סוכה Sukkah. *Sukkah*. But we're talking that the planks are at
the edge of the סוכה Sukkah *Sukkah* and if they're at the
edge of the סוכה Sukkah. *Sukkah*, whatever, you get the idea. Anyway,
if they're at the edge of the סוכה sukkah, *Sukkah* only once
it is four אמות amot *Amot* will it invalidate, any less than
that we will bend the wall. Okay, so what have we done
now? We've brought a משנה *Mishnah* and a ברייתא *Braita* which seem
to say the משנה *Mishnah* seems to say four טפחים tefachim *Tefachim*
is enough to create a
problem. And excuse me, no excuse me, both of them. The משנה
*Mishnah* said that four טפחים tefachim *Tefachim* itself does not create a
problem, a proof that you need more than four טפחים tefachim *Tefachim*.
And the answer is no, no, no, we're talking about at the
side of the סוכה sukkah, *Sukkah*. The ברייתא *Braita* also implicitly says
four טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* is not enough to create a problem, you
need to combine them. And we have the same answer, that's because
we'll say that the case is we're talking at the side of
the סוכה sukkah *Sukkah*. So any scenario you bring me that shows
that four טפחים tefachim *Tefachim* is not a problem and would seem
to support an idea that you need four אמות amot *Amot* in
the middle, I'll tell you that's a scenario that's talking on the
side and that's why it's not a problem. So that's how we're
going to get out of those ברייתות braitos *Braitas* and משנות *Mishnot*
that seem to prove רב'ס *Rav's* position that you need four אמות
amot. *Amot* in the middle because anything that seems to say that
we'll say we're talking not in the middle but on the side.
Yes, a question about מן הצד min ha-tzad. *Min hatzad*. Can you
combine both גוד אסיק gud assik *Gud asik* and דופן עקומה Dofen
Akumah *Dofen akuma*?
No, because the whole idea is that you need the physical continuation
of the wall. Oh, actually no, that's an interesting question. You can't
have a non-wall at the beginning part of the roof. Can you
have a מחיצה mechitza, *Mechitzah* down here, do a גוד אסיק asig,
*Gud asik* and then use the bend? I think you are able
to do that.
But not at the top.
There's not at the top, not at the top. I think there's
a ר"ן *Ran* about that. I'll have to I'll double check that.
I think you are able to do that. Okay, so that's anyway
that's how we got out of those proofs that seem to say
four טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* does not invalidate, that we're talking about the
side. תא שמע *Ta shema*, let's try again. סיככה בנסרים של ארז
*Sikcha bensarim shel erez*,
you put cedar planks on your on your סוכה sukkah. *Sukkah*. שיש
בהן ארבע *Sheyesh bahen arba*, they're four טפחים tefachim *Tefachim* wide. דברי
הכל פסולה *Divrei hakol pesulah*,
everybody would agree it's invalid. This is the ברייתא *Braita* that that
supports the idea that that the debate of רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir*
and רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* is only between three and four. Once
it's four טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* everybody agrees it's invalid. Okay, so that's
what it's saying. If it's four טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* even רבי יהודה
*Rebbe Yehuda* would agree it's invalid. אין בהן ארבע *Ein bahen arba*,
if it's not four טפחים tefachim *Tefachim*, it's between three and four.
That's the debate of רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* and רבי יהודה *Rebbe
Yehuda*. רבי מאיר פוסל ורבי יהודה מכשיר *Rebbe Meir posel veRebbe Yehuda
machshir*. Okay, that's what we've seen before, a debate of planks, here
being framed as between three and four. But now becomes the interesting
line for us, top of י"ח עמוד א' *Yud chet amud aleph*.
ומודה רבי מאיר *U'modeh Rebbe Meir*, Rebbe Meir will concede שאם יש
בין נסר לנסר כמלא נסר *she'im yesh bein neser leneser kemlo neser*,
if between
a plank and a plank there is the gap of a plank,
שמניח פסל psal. *she'maniach pesal*, again
so interesting that kosher סכך skhach. *Sechach* is called פסל *Pesal*, you
put the kosher סכך skhach. *Sechach* ביניהם וכשרה *beineihem u'kesherah*, and it's
kosher. Okay so you have this סוכה sukkah. *Sukkah* made of
these planks which are between three and four, so or actually we're
going to assume here four, okay, so it'll be because
the debate of רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* and רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*
is between three and four but everybody agrees it's invalid with four
טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim*. So you have these things which look excuse me,
that doesn't look like a plank, that looks like פסל *Pesal*. You
have these planks
which are four טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* wide, okay, and they have and
there's a gap here between them. Okay these are four טפחים tefachim,
*Tefachim* wide, even רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* says that they're פסולה *Pesulah*.
But even רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* who's more strict would say that
if you come and you fill this with kosher סכך skhach. *Sechach*
and this is also four טפחים tefachim. *Tefachim*, that it's kosher. Now
how the heck could that be? How did your סוכה sukkah *Sukkah*
become kosher? I mean you've got all this פסול סכך pasul sechach.
*Pesul sechach* breaking it up, right? So if you say that you
normally need right four אמות amot *Amot* to invalidate your סוכה sukkah,
*Sukkah*,
you
don't have four אמות amot...
*Amot* of פסול סכך pasul sechach, *Pesul sechach*. So obviously don't sit
under the under the פסול pasul *Pesul* edges, but the סוכה sukkah.
*Sukkah* itself can be kosher with zones you can eat in and
zones you can't. Fine, but at least it doesn't invalidate the סוכה
sukkah *Sukkah*. It's just a סוכה sukkah, *Sukkah* with like I said
different zones. But if four טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* invalidate, how does this
solve the problem? Okay so let's take a look.
One thing that's amazing, four טפחים tefachim, *Tefachim* is so wide. I
know, even four טפחים tefachim *Tefachim* is a foot. No, it's not
like a foot. Okay anyway. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
בשלמא says the גמרא, Gemara למאן דאמר leman de-amar בין באמצע בין
בצד bein be-emtza bein be-tzad בארבע אמות, if even in the middle
it doesn't invalidate the סוכה sukkah, until you have ארבע אמות, arba
amot, משום הכי כשרה. mishum hachi kesherah. So the סוכה sukkah. is
כשרה. kesherah? Yes, don't sleep or don't eat under the four טפחים
tefachim פסול. pasul Four טפחים פסול pasul marks out a big enough
zone. If it's less than four טפחים, by the way, you could
even eat under the סכך. skhach But four טפחים under the פסול
סכך, pasul sechach but four טפחים marks out a big enough zone
that it's its own space and don't eat under. Fine, but the
סוכה sukkah. remains כשרה kesherah just with different zones. אלא למאן דאמר
באמצע בארבעה, ela le-man de-amar be-emtza be-arba'ah, but if in the middle,
if four טפחים is enough to invalidate the סוכה, sukkah. אמאי כשרה,
kesheira, how does doing this alternating make the סוכה succa. כשרה? kesheira.
Every single plank should invalidate the סוכה. succa The גמרא Gemara now
here, here we, it's like a gotcha because every time the גמרא
Gemara until now has been trying to prove that four טפחים doesn't
invalidate, we said, oh, what are we talking about? When it says
that four טפחים is a problem, we're talking מן הצד. But you
can't do it here because here it says you're alternating the whole
roof. Oh, we're just talking on the side. What do you mean?
We're alternating the whole roof. But guess what? The גמרא Gemara. is
going to figure out how we're going to turn this into a
case where it's מן הצד. Let's see how. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna
breih de-Rav Yehoshua, says Rav Huna the son of Rav Yehoshua, הכא
בסוכה דלא הויא אלא שמונה מצומצמות עסקינן. hacha be-sukkah de-la havya ela
shemoneh metzumtzamot askinan. The סוכה succa? is only exactly eight אמות, excuse
me, eight אמות. ויהיב נסר ופסל ונסר ופסל ונסר ופסל מהאי גיסא,
ve-yahiv neser u-psal ve-neser u-psal ve-neser u-psal me-hai gisa, ונסר ופסל ונסר
ופסל ונסר ופסל מהאי גיסא. ve-neser u-psal ve-neser u-psal ve-neser u-psal me-hai
gisa. Okay, that basically you've got a סוכה succa, that is eight
אמות wide, okay, and what you do is you start alternating on
this side up till here. You know, let's just imagine you've been
alternating, this represents the whole length, and here is your four אמות
mark when you get to the פסל. Okay, you've alternated all the
way up to four אמות on that side. Then you do the
other side, but you don't keep on going. Okay, you start the
same way on the other side. So way back here you start
the same way, right? So in the middle you get the same
thing coming from both sides. You started the same way when you
get to the middle, right at the four אמות mark you have
here eight טפחים of כשר סכך. kasher sechach, And, but okay, but
it's smack in the middle of the סוכה. Ah, but because each
side here is less than four אמות, right, because it was three
אמות and two טפחים and then you added a טפח. tefach Each
side, what you do is that lets you bend the wall here
and bend the wall here and make it into a כשרה סוכה
in the middle. Which means that we've turned this into into מן
הצד. We basically have, every time we've proven that four טפחים is
not a problem, we said we're talking on the side. Ah, look,
it's not a problem it's in the middle. No no no, it's
really מן הצד. You really got this whole thing becoming your wall
and therefore in the middle you can get your כשר סכך. kasher
sechach, But we're doing דופן עקומה Dofen Akumah? over כשר kosher סכך.
sechach, Yes, that you can do. You can incorporate the כשר kosher
סכך. sechach, Any פסול סכך pasul sechach, within four אמות of the
wall, right, gets incorporated into the wall. Could you remind us, was
there a פסוק pasuk from which the חכמים chachamim learn דופן עקומה?
Dofen Akumah. No no no, it's all like הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai. That was gonna be my next question. Even though they
don't say הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. Well no, the גמרא
Gemara actually did say that. הלכות, hilchot, אסיק, and דופן עקומה. dofen
akuma Yeah, the גמרא Gemara actually said at the bottom of ו,
vav, no at the bottom of ה עמוד ב. hei amud bet.
It said, where was it? Yeah, the שיעורין. shiurin. Yeah, one minute.
Oh no maybe it was ו עמוד ב. vav amud bet. Hold
on a minute. Yeah, the middle of ו עמוד ב. vav amud
bet. The גמרא Gemara says so what's the point about חציצה chatzitzah
that מחיצות mechitzot is הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai? So it
says כי אתא הלכתא לגוד ולבוד ודופן עקומה. ki ata hilchata le-gud
u-levud ve-dofen akumah. Right smack, right the top third of ה עמוד
ב hei amud bet by the תוספות. Tosfot. That's a הלכתא hilchata
which it normally is understood to mean הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha le-Moshe
mi-Sinai, okay, which was sort of said before is גוד ולבוד ודופן
עקומה. gud u-levud ve-dofen akumah. All of these principles. Okay. Yeah, it
is an important one. Okay, back to our גמרא. Gemara Okay, so
now we've dealt with the textual evidence. Let's realize that all the
textual evidence supports רב. All the textual evidence supports the idea that
four טפחים is not enough to invalidate the סוכה. And we've turned
all of those cases into cases of מן הצד. Okay, so let's
take a look. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: עוביה שלושה. Oviya shlosha. Now
we're moving on beyond this debate of four אמות and four טפחים.
The גמרא Gemara didn't clearly rule, but we rule even four טפחים
in the middle is the problem. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: עוביה שלושה
בסוכה גדולה ומיעטו, בין בקנים בין בשפודין הוי מיעוט. Oviya shlosha besukkah
gedolah umiato, bein bekanim bein bishpudin havei miyut. בסוכה קטנה, Besukkah ketana,
if it's a minimum size סוכה, exactly seven טפחים by seven טפחים,
בקנים הוי מיעוט. bekanim havei miyut. So if you fill the gap
with כשר kosher סכך, sechach you solve the problem. No kidding. Even
if you didn't fill the gap, even if you just filled part
of it, the rest you say לבוד, lavud, so you solve the
problem. בשפודין לא הוי מיעוט, Bishpudin lo havei miyut, but if you
put פסול סכך pasul schach, there, it does not, it does not
solve the problem. Okay, והני מילי. ve-hani mili. So now why not?
So because this is what we saw before, you might remember yesterday,
אביי Abaye assumed that in a small סוכה, the שיעור shiur was
three טפחים of פסול סכך. pasul schach Three טפחים of air, three
טפחים of פסול pasul. סכך. sechach That was אביי Abaye's assumption. Well
now we're hearing him spell it out, but he doesn't tell us
why. But you have a סוכה that's exactly seven by seven, okay?
And what he would say is, so if you have air that
is three טפחים, right here, then obviously it breaks it up. That's
even in a big סוכה. But if you have in there פסול
סכך, schach אביי Abaye would say the following. He would say look,
I know that פסול סכך schach normally doesn't break up the thing
and isn't a problem until it's four, until it's four טפחים minimally.
That's what we've been saying. But once it's three טפחים, at least
it defines enough of its own space that you can't incorporate that
space into the parameters of the סוכה. So this is like a
brand new idea, not based on anything we saw before. I admit
it does not break up the סכך, s’chach but it says this
is already enough of a segment that it's its own zone, that
it does not just get collapsed into the two other sides, that
now you cannot say you've got a סוכה seven by seven, because
now this, at least a piece of the סוכה, you cannot be
considered incorporated as part of the size of the סוכה. Isn't that
the same as saying you can't sit underneath it? You can't sit
underneath it? No, because actually in a normal סוכה of less than
four טפחים you could sit underneath it. Less than... correct. Yeah, so
but he's not, he's not saying that. He's not introducing that. He's
just saying it's a new idea he has, again, that if you
have to figure out what are the dimensions of my סוכה, so
when you have such a small סוכה, you cannot incorporate that into
the dimensions. I guess the idea is like, you know, if you
get like, imagine something like this. This is a very loose analogy,
okay? You know, you want to know how much, what's it called,
floor space you have in your apartment. You've got a nice big
apartment, so okay, you know, you include, you include like the bathroom
floor space and the space taken up by the thickness of the
walls. You know, do you include that? No. But imagine now you've
got this tiny little studio Manhattan apartment, right? So you're so tiny
that it's not, you can't count that little space as part of
the floor space because it's not really, you know, it's not like
you already have living space you don't have to include. Anyway, that's
my loose analogy. Okay, but the point is once it's so small,
every space matters, and if you have even three טפחים, it cannot
be incorporated into the dimensions of the סוכה. Fine, that was implicit
before, now he's saying it explicitly. The גמרא Gemara doesn't dwell on
it. It's obviously a new idea of אביי. Abaye. Okay, or אביי
Abaye assumed that רבא Rava agreed to it yesterday, you'll remember. Okay,
now the גמרא gemara says like this. Now, והני מילי מן הצד.
ve-hani mili min hatzad. This is not going on אביי. Abaye. When
do we say לבוד lavud works? When have we been assuming לבוד
lavud works? If it's at the edge of a סוכה. It's a
gap between the wall and the סכך, s’chach. less than three טפחים,
it's closed. He says, אבל באמצע, aval be'emtza, the same way we
were discussing how much סכך s’chach. invalidates in the middle, and the
middle could be different than the edge, right? That was our whole
discussion so far today. The גמרא Gemara saying, let's have the same
discussion by the gap of air. Maybe the gap of air, three
טפחים works at the edge, but doesn't work in the middle, right?
The same way we have a different problem in the middle by
פסול סכך, s’chach. maybe we have a different problem in the middle
by air. Rabbi Maimon, how did you know that והני מילי מן
הצד ve-hani mili min hatzad isn't going back to לבוד? lavud? Because
of רש״י. Rashi. It's very confusing. I would never without looking, because
of רש״י, Rashi, he says we're now going back to the more
general... At the edge, but doesn't work in the middle, right? The
same way we have a different problem in the middle by פסול
סכך, s’chach, maybe we have a different problem in the middle by
אויר. avir. Rabbi, how did you know that והני מילי מן הצד
ve-hanei milei min ha-tzad refers back to? Because of רש״י. Rashi. Because
of רש״י. Rashi. It's very confusing. Right. Right. How'd you ever without
looking? Because of רש״י, Rashi, he says we're now going back to
the more general point, as the גמרא Gemara continues, it could be
part of אביי, Abaye, but it's not, because it's going to introduce
a new debate. No, not at all. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay. But
anyway, you're right, only because of רש״י. Rashi. It's definitely a confusing
transition. אבל באמצע, aval be-emtza, if you have the gap of air
in the middle, right, maybe just like פסול סכך s’chach is different
in the middle, maybe that's worse in terms of air. So that's
פליגי רב אחא ורבינא. pligi Rav Acha ve-Ravina. That's the debate of
רב אחא ורבינא. Rav Acha ve-Ravina. חד אמר chad amar one says
יש לבוד באמצע yesh lavud be-emtza that there is לבוד lavud in
the middle. And why not, right? לבוד lavud is a principle we
always apply, so any less than three טפחים, wherever it occurs, side,
middle, who knows, who cares, we close the gap. וחד אמר ve-chad
amar but one says אין לבוד באמצע. ein lavud be-emtza. Nope, in
the middle of a roof you cannot say לבוד, lavud, which is
crazy, right? We never have heard any limit of לבוד. lavud. We
say לבוד lavud all the time. So תוספות, Tosafot, by the way,
I should say, is sensitive to this. Like he says, what do
you mean? We got like classic לבוד lavuds where you make a
virtual wall out of like sticks that are three טפחים, you know,
from one another. That's all this middle space, it's not just edge
space. So תוספות Tosafot says no, we're talking about roofs. For some
reason, we know that in all the rest of the world, like
when talking about like walls and things like that, you can say
לבוד lavud whether it's the middle or the edges. But here's an
opinion that for some reason, when it comes to a roof, you
can only say לבוד lavud at the edge, not at the middle.
So we're going now bring proofs from משניות mishnayos and ברייתות that
deal with roofs that say whether you can say לבוד lavud even
in the middle of a roof. Okay, for some reason maybe the
middle of a roof is different. If the משנה says you cannot
use לבוד lavud in the... well no, this is three... once it's
three טפחים, it's no longer לבוד. lavud. So we're no longer... it
always has to be less than three טפחים. We're no longer in
a בית, bayit, okay? Or all I was going to say is
that if you... like maybe the מחלוקת machloket is, is a ceiling
a wall flipped or not? Yeah, but it's still... yeah, okay, let's
take a look. Because the גמרא Gemara says like this. So חד
אמר יש לבוד באמצע וחד אמר אין לבוד באמצע. chad amar yesh
lavud be-emtza ve-chad amar ein lavud be-emtza. מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר יש
לבוד באמצע? mai ta'ama de-man de-amar yesh lavud be-emtza? What's the reason
that you say לבוד lavud applies even in the middle, the middle
of a ceiling? דתניא de-tanya as shown in a ברייתא: קורה היוצא
מכותל זה ואינה נוגעת בכותל אחר. kora ha-yotze mi-kotel ze ve-eina noga'at
be-kotel acher. Let's say you have a beam—this is for the הלכות
halachot of שבת, Shabbat, like a חצר chatzer that has three walls
and you need, in order to carry in it, either a לחי
lechi at the entranceway or a קורה kora across the entranceway for
the fourth side. Right, people know that principle לחי או קורה. lechi
o kora. So you've got a beam. The beam doesn't get to
the opposite wall ואינה נוגעת בכותל אחר. ve-eina noga'at be-kotel acher. וכן
שתי קורות ve-chen shtei korot or if you have two beams, אחת
יוצאת מכותל זה ואחת יוצאת מכותל אחר, achat yotzet mi-kotel ze ve-achat
yotzet mi-kotel acher, one coming out of one wall, one coming out
of the other wall, ואינן נוגעות זו בזו, ve-einan nogot zu be-zo,
and they meet in the middle but they don't touch. Sort of
like when they were building the Channel, you know, and that was
also the חזקיהו Chizkiyahu's tunnel, right, that's like amazing. You know, it
took half the time it took to build it, but the need
of precision in order to be able to come from both ends
and get in the middle, that they did it in modern technology
is not such a חידוש, chiddush, but they did it even in
like חזקיהו Chizkiyahu's tunnel. Anyway, okay. So anyway, so they meet in
the middle and they don't touch, ואינן נוגעות זו בזו. ve-einan nogot
zu be-zo. So פחות משלושה אינו צריך להביא קורה אחרת. pachot mi-shlosha
eino tzarich le-havi kora acheret. If the gap between the קורה kora
and the wall, or between the two קורות, korot, is less than
three טפחים, you don't need to fill in the gap. שלושה, shlosha,
once it's three טפחים, צריך להביא קורה אחרת, tzarich le-havi kora acheret,
you have to fill it in with another קורה kora because... so
what does it show you? It shows you you say לבוד, lavud,
you treat it as connected, whether you're connecting it to the opposite
wall or whether you're connecting two קורות korot באמצע. באמצע you can
connect, and that's more like an idea of a roof because it's
something that's above, קורה, kora, okay? Which is funny because, you know,
there's an opinion that says קורה משום מחיצה. kora mishum mechitza. The
way the קורה kora functions by being this beam up there is
that it sort of creates a virtual wall beneath it. So even
though its function is to be a מחיצה, since sort of geographically,
you know, it is about something that's running vertical and not something
that's running horizontal, that we think that it might have different laws
of לבוד. lavud. And here it says, look, you see it doesn't
have different laws of לבוד, lavud, you can say it. ואידך? ve-idach?
So what would the other opinion say back to that? שאני קורות
דרבנן. shani korot de-rabbanan. Yeah, that's all rabbinic, you know, the need
for a קורה kora once you already have three walls. Here we're
talking about a biblical idea of a requirement, דאורייתא de-oraita requirement of
סוכה. That's different. That's going to... that you won't get away with
לבוד. lavud. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר אין
לבוד באמצע? mai ta'ama de-man de-amar ein lavud be-emtza? Now yeah, what's
the basis of saying there isn't לבוד באמצע? lavud be-emtza? Like that's
bizarre, we never hear the idea that you can't say לבוד. lavud.
דתנן, de-tnan, we taught in a משנה by טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-tahara
and by the idea of an אהל המת, ohel ha-met, right, a
corpse and a body under a roof, the roof conveys the טומאה
tumah and stops the טומאה tumah from going above. So ארובה שבבית,
aruba she-be-bayit, you have a skylight in your house. Skylight is obviously
in the middle of the roof. ובה פותח טפח, uva poteach tefach,
and there is a טפח, tefach it's a טפח tefach, by טפח
tefach. wide. טומאה בבית, tumah babayis, כולו טמא. kulo tamei. If there's
טומאה tumah in the house, then the house itself is fully טמא.
tamei. מה שכנגד ארובה טהור. ma shekeneged aruba tahor. What's opposite the
ארובה, aruba, the skylight remains טהור. tahor. Okay, because basically what you've
got is, right, here's your roof, here's your skylight, it's a טפח,
tefach and you've got your טומאה tumah somewhere in the house, you've
got your טומאה tumah over here. So what happens to the טומאה?
tumah? It spreads throughout the house, right? It goes under the roof
as it were, and the roof determines the area which it spreads,
but it's not going to spread in the zone, that column created
by the skylight, because there's no roof over that column. So everything
in the house is טמא tamei except, you know, this should be
another color, okay, except the zone created right by the skylight, because
there's no roof in that zone, so the טומאה tumah doesn't get
communicated to the zone directly beneath the skylight. So if you have
some vessel directly beneath the skylight, it is טהור. tahor. Okay, clear?
Yep. Okay. So... טומאה כנגד ארובה, tumah keneged aruba, let's say you've
got the טומאה tumah underneath the skylight. מה שכנגד ארובה... ma shekeneged
aruba... טומאה כנגד ארובה, tumah keneged aruba, כל הבית כולו טהור, kol
habayis kulo tahor, then the house is saved, because there's no roof
to bring it to the rest of the house. Okay, and now,
what would happen though if over here that somebody above the ארובה
aruba would get טמא, tamei, because there's also no roof to block
it? Okay, but if it's in this zone, then it doesn't have
a roof and the rest of the בית bayis remains טהור. tahor.
Okay. Now, אין בארובה פותח טפח, ein baaruba poteach tefach, let's say
the skylight doesn't have a טפח. tefach, So in that case, טומאה
בבית, tumah babayis, כנגד ארובה טהור. keneged aruba tahor. Opposite the skylight
remains טהור. tahor. טומאה כנגד ארובה, tumah keneged aruba, if there's טומאה
tumah underneath the skylight, כל הבית כולו טהור, kol habayis kulo tahor,
the rest of the house remains טהור. tahor. Do you see any
difference between the second one, as it were, the הלכה halacha of
the second and the first? It's the exact same הלכה. halacha. So
רש״י Rashi says, acknowledges that, and he says the only reason it's
describing two cases, one of a טפח tefach and one less than
a טפח, tefach, is because there are other הלכות halachos in which
they're different, which is part, it's in the משנה where it appears.
Okay, so the משנה goes into saying these ways it's the same,
but there are other distinctions between the... that is made by the
size of the ארובה. aruba. Okay, but in this, for this הלכה,
halacha, it's identical. However big the ארובה aruba is, it creates a
zone underneath it, and if the טומאה tumah is here, that zone
is saved, if the טומאה tumah is in the zone, then the
rest of the house is saved. Whether it's a טפח tefach or
not a טפח, tefach that is not a difference. So that's why
they say סיפא גרסינן כי רישא, seifa garsinan ki reisha, the end
of it is exactly... the end is exactly the same as the
beginning, exact same הלכה, halacha, but fine, the difference is in another
area. Now, what's his point? His point is, if we would say
לבוד באמצע, lavud beamtza, what should you say in this case? What
should you say in the case of the skylight? If you have
a one-טפח skylight and you normally say לבוד, lavud, what should you
say? Does the skylight create a safe zone underneath it? No, because
you should see it as closed! How can it be in the
laws of טומאה tumah you can have a hole in your roof
and it's a significant hole and it creates a zone, it should
be just insignificant, it should lose its identity based on לבוד? lavud?
So that's the reason I think that holes in roofs are different.
So גמרא Gemara says ואידך יהבו ליה צד באה, veidach yahavu lei
tzad baah, no. שאני הלכות טומאה, shani hilchos tumah, that's its own
category. והכי גמירי לה, vehachi gmiri lah, that's a particular tradition they
have. So that category of טומאה, tumah, you don't go applying laws
of טומאה tumah to other areas. You want to generalize that case,
I'm saying that case is an exception, and the general rule is
the rule that לבוד lavud you always say. Right, for physical entities
it's closed and for metaphysical entities it's open. Okay, say it that
way. Now, דרש רב יהודה בריה דרבי אלעאי. darash Rav Yehuda brei
de-Rabbi Ilai. Now רב יהודה בריה דרבי אלעאי Rav Yehuda brei de-Rabbi
Ilai expounded in the following way: בית שנפחת וסיכך על גביו כשרה.
bayis shenifchat vesichach al gabav kesheira. So you have a house, this
is going back to a simple case of a bending wall, now
the bending wall is a simple case. Goes back to a simple
case of a bending wall, a little section in the middle of
the roof fell out and you filled it with כשר kosher סכך,
כשרה, it's kosher. Now the word דרש darash is funny, right? Why
doesn't it say אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אלעאי, amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav Ilai, you know, blah, blah, blah, because we're going to
see that there was an exchange that took place, so he apparently
was somewhere like in public giving a lecture, okay, it's not like
a דרשה drasha like, you know, like we're going to have an
interpretation of a פסוק pasuk from the פרשה, parsha, but he was
somewhere giving a public lecture and teaching this to people, it was
ערב סוכות, erev Sukkos, and he said if you've got a hole
in the middle of your roof and you put סכך on it,
it's still כשר. kosher. Okay, that's what he said in his דרשה.
drasha. אמר לפניו רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. amar lefanav Rabbi Yishmael berabbi
Yossi. So רב ישמעאל... Rabbi Yishmael... said, רבי, פריש, parish, רבי, you
should explain what you're saying, you know, you can't just say it's
כשר. kosher. כך דאבא, Kach de'Abba, here's how my father explained the
case, רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. ארבע אמות פסולה, Arba amot psula, if
it's ארבע אמות, arba amot, if the סכך in the middle of
your roof is ארבע אמות arba amot removed from the wall, then
it's invalid. You can't bend the wall that far. פחות מארבע אמות
כשרה, Pachot mi-arba amot keshera, less than that it's valid. Don't just
say it's כשר, kosher, you're giving a public lecture, you've got to
explain what you're saying. It's כשר kosher if it's less than ארבע
אמות arba amot from this סכך in the middle of the house
of the roof to the wall. Okay, now we have another case.
דרש רבי יהודה ברבי אלעאי, Darash Rabbi Yehuda be-Rabbi Ilai, רבי יהודה
ברבי אלעאי Rabbi Yehuda be-Rabbi Ilai got up and he expounded like
in public the following thing. אברומה שריא. Avruma sharya. אברומה, Avruma, which
is a type of a fish, is permissible. And apparently there was
a question, you know nowadays we go crazy about all this stuff
around bugs, and you know is this like a recent invention or
not, take a look at רש"י Rashi two lines down on the
wide lines. אברומה, Avruma, רש"י Rashi says, מין דגים קטנים ואין שרצים
ניכרים בהם. min dagim ktanim ve'ein shratzim nikarim bahem. Okay, it is
a small fish and tiny little bugs might get embedded in the
skin of the fish and they're not so obvious. Okay, so this
is the question. Can you eat this אברומה Avruma or not? Do
you have to concern yourself about tiny bugs that you might not
be paying attention to? It's just a speck. Okay, so he says
it's permissible. אמר לפניו רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Amar lefanev Rabbi Yishmael
be-Rabbi Yosi. So רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yosi was
there and he said, רבי, פריש, parish, רבי, explain what you're saying,
you have to qualify it. כך אמר אבא. Kach amar Abba. Here's
what my father said. שמקום פלוני אסורה. she-makom ploni asura. The fish
of place X, he obviously said what the X was, is forbidden.
שמקום פלוני מותרת. she-makom ploni mutara. Case Y, the fish in place
Y is permissible. You can't just say it's permissible. You gotta say
what situation you're talking about. So now, what's the explanation of the
different places? היי דאמר אביי, Hai d'amar Abaye, like אביי Abaye said.
היי סכנתא, Hai sakhanta, this סכנתא, sakhanta, which is another type of
a fish, okay, דבב נהרא de-Bav Nahara in the river, in the
river בב, Bav, that was the name of the river, שריא, sharya,
are permissible. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? And you don't have to worry
about the, you know, about the little parasites that might be in
it, like little bugs that might be in it. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? What's the reason? אילימא משום דרדיפי מיא? Ileima mishum de-radifei maya?
If it's because that river, the water is rushing, והאי דג טמא?
ve-hai dag tamei? And these, it's calling the concern of these embedded
bugs or שרצים shratzim as a דג טמא, dag tamei, meaning it's
a טמא tamei thing that grows in the water. Okay, and these
טמא tamei bugs, כיון דלית להו חוט השדרה, keivan de-leis lehu huta
deshishra, since they don't have a spine, לא מצי קיימי, lo matzi
kaymi, they can't survive in rushing water. Okay, that's an interesting idea,
spine gives you some backbone. These fish that don't have a spine,
you actually, it's the opposite, you'd think if you don't have a
spine you're more flexible, it's easier. Anyway, what doesn't have the spine?
The fish? The שרצים, shratzim, the bugs, okay, but it's being called
here דג טמא. dag tamei. And that's why you don't have to
worry about them. והא קא חזינן דקיימי? ve-ha ka khazinan de-kaymi? But
we actually see that these types of bugs are, exist in rushing
water. By the way, quite fascinating that the גמרא is actually, you
know, bringing empirical evidence. Right, very often it will debate certain things
based on, you know, about the real world based on פסוקים pesukim
or based on other things, you know, and it's interesting when it
actually says let's look at the empirical evidence. Well, so isn't the
visibility of the bugs a... Yes, but the גמרא isn't dealing with
that. The גמרא isn't dealing with the issue of visibility. That's a
question for practical הלכה, halacha, that's not what the גמרא is addressing.
Okay, so the גמרא says אלא משום ד ela mishum de I'm
sorry, I slipped. אלא משום דמליחי מיא? Ela mishum de-malihei maya? Maybe
it's because the water is salty? והאי דג טמא, ve-hai dag tamei,
and this שרץ sheratz that you're
concerned with, כיון דלית ליה קלפי, keivan de-leis lehu kilfei,
since it does not have scales, לא מצי קיימי, lo matzi kaymi,
maybe it can't survive the harsh conditions of salty water. But that's
not true. והא קא חזינן דקיימי. ve-ha ka khazinan de-kaymi. We see
that they do live in salty water. אלא משום דלא מרבי טינא
האי דג טמא. Ela mishum de-lo marbei tina hai dag tamei. It
must be that the mud of that river does not literally like
cause, you know, grow these טרף treif fish. So again, it's a
little funny after the empirical evidence it says the mud doesn't grow
טרף treif fish. Okay, but maybe, you know, fish actually grow because
the eggs, right, are planted, so maybe it's saying, you know, it
can't sustain the birthing of טרף treif fish, of these טרף treif
fish. So in this river you don't have to worry about it
because basically it's the way of saying these bugs are not present
in this river. It's like saying, oh, you can't drink the New
York City water, that has the copepods, but the Riverdale water, that
you can drink because that's a different source of water and therefore
you don't have to worry about the bugs. Okay, so אמר רבינא,
amar Ravina, so says רבינא, Ravina, והאידנא, ve-idna, nowadays, דשפכי נהר איתן
ונהר גמדא להתם. de-shafchi Nahar Eitan ve-Nahar Gamda le-hasam. other rivers now
have somehow diverted and empty into this river that was not a
problem, but now they're getting fish from other rivers, so nowadays אסירא
assira everything is forbidden. Okay, so that was a fascinating little digression
but again it was a case where רבי יהודה was giving a
public lecture and רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yosi was
saying you can't just say מותר. muttar. You have to be a
little bit more clear what parameters you're talking about. Now איתמר, itmar,
it was taught: סיככה על גבי אכסדרה שיש לה פצימין. sikcha al
gabei achsadra she-yesh la patzimin. You put סכך on a אכסדרה, achsadra,
on a portico, that has פצימין patzimin which are like posts. Okay,
so you’ve got your nice little yard.
As רש״י Rashi says, your oyster, you've got your yard, okay? It's
got building back here, okay?
and it's got a portico that sort of runs along the—no, wait,
I mean it's got like a roof that runs like you know
whatever and it's got this and maybe it's got some columns that
are holding it up. You sort of get the idea? Okay, so
these are the פצימין. patzimin. If it's got not just the back
wall which is the house but it has columns right towards where
you want to put your סוכה. So you want to put your
סוכה here, okay? Right? That's what you want to do. Okay, now
the question here is let's assume that this is like more than
four אמות or whatever. You can't use the wall. So let's assume
there are no walls back there, you can't bend the walls to
use it. Okay? Can you use the columns here to make to
give you your kosher סוכה? So it says like this: Okay, so
this is more than—this is more than four אמות. Yeah, let's say
this is a five אמות overhang. So you cannot bend the wall.
But what you want to do is you want to use the
colonnade, you want you want to use the—the posts that are—no, to
be if they're—to be able to look at them as the wall.
Okay, so those are the ones that are closest to the סכך.
Oh, okay, so so the colonnade, the columns are not five אמות...
No, the columns are right at the edge of the סכך. They're
at the edge, right. The columns are right at the edge of
the סכך. Here's your walk-in a little—yeah, yeah, yeah. Anyway, so okay,
so what? I have to erase it. Okay, so anyway, okay, סיככה
על גבי אכסדרה שיש לה פצימין. sikcha al gabei achsadra she-yesh la
patzimin. כשרה. Now, if it's got these colonnades and those colonnades are
let's say within three טפחים of one another—that's the assumption that we're
talking about—then that serves as a wall. Fine. שאין לה פצימין, she-ein
la patzimin, but if it doesn't have posts that can be used,
they're at, you know, they're they're too distant from one another, whatever
the situation is, the posts can't be used, אביי אמר כשרה, Abaye
amar kesheira, it's still kosher, ורבא אמר פסולה, ve-Rava amar pesula, it's
פסול. Now, how could it be kosher? Where are the walls? So
אביי אמר כשרה, Abaye amar kesheira, אביי Abaye says it's kosher. Ha,
see? You thought we weren't going to finish the דף daf today.
אמרינן פי תקרה יורד וסותם. amrinan pi tikra yored ve-sotem. This is
a new idea. You thought we were done with דופן עקומה dofen
akuma. and גוד אסיק and לבוד? lavud? No. What אביי Abaye is
saying is like this: If you've got a roof that ends in
a nice square way, okay, if that's the end edge of your
roof, okay, then this edge of the roof can be looked at
as the beginning of a wall. Let's assume that there's some significant
width there, like a טפח or something. Maybe not, but let's assume.
Then that could be looked up as as your wall, as the
beginning of your wall, and you would say the edge of the
roof goes down and closes off that area. Okay? So now you
don't need—if you have just normal, let's say סכך, it's little sticks,
it's not squared off, you can't use that trick, okay? But in
this case, what did you do? Here you are walking underneath the
portico, right? You know, etcetera, right? And you're putting סכך this way,
right? So you use the edge of the beams of the portico
to go down and to be considered like a wall, okay? So
that's like a really, you know, wild idea. Until now we've been
thinking maybe you can do ten טפחים at the bottom and then
maybe you can't but then it continues up, but to be able
to use when you have a squared-off roof around it the edge
of the beams and to say it goes down, that is the
idea of פי תקרה יורד וסותם. pi tikra yored ve-sotem. It's the
opposite of דופן עקומה. Instead of the wall going up and then
over... right, the wall's coming down through the roof going down. Yes,
פי תקרה, pi tikra, good memory. פי תקרה יורד וסותם pi tikra
yored ve-sotem is not just for סוכה, yes, and עירוב, eruv, a
lot of these things are ideas—not the bending wall because you don't
need a rooftop by עירוב—but eruv yes. רבא אמר פסולה, Rava amar
pesula, it's invalid. לא אמרינן פי תקרה יורד וסותם, lo amrinan pi
tikra yored ve-sotem, you don't say it. Now, there's a big... Today,
רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafot*, which is what these huge תוספות *Tosafots*
here are about, between how many walls do you need? Are we
saying that you can use it for all three walls? That's what
רש"י *Rashi* says, okay, but that's very hard to read the גמרא
*Gemara* like רש"י *Rashi*, you should know that רש"י'ס *Rashi's* opinion is
that the one that says it's כשר *kosher* says you can use
it for all the walls. תוספות *Tosafot* says, תוספות *Tosafot* says nobody
is suggesting that. According to תוספות *Tosafot*, at most you can use
this concept to give you your third wall. So תוספות *Tosafot* wants
to say that the scenario is you've built a wall here and
you've built a wall here and you want to use it just
to give you your third wall. That's how תוספות *Tosafot* explains it,
we're going to read the גמרא *Gemara* that way, okay? And that
fits with the continuation. So let's take a look. One thing, does
anyone think that the roof had to be three טפחים *tefachim* with?
What? The roof? You know for a שיעור תקרה *shiur tikra*? I'd
have to check, I don't think. Doesn't it say it in some
places? No no no no no, I think that there's a position
of a טפח *tefach*, okay, but not three, certainly not three טפחים
*tefachim*. Okay, but I need to check that. Okay, so the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this: אמר ליה רבא לאביי *Amar lei Rava l'Abaye*,
so רבא *Rava* said to אביי *Abaye*, לדידך דאמרת פי תקרה יורד
וסותם *l'didach d'amart pi tikra yored v'sotem*, you say you can close
it off, so if that's true, אפילו הפחית דופן אמצעי *afilu hifchit
dofen emtzai*? What if the scenario was not these two, these two
walls you have, but let's say in an expanded סוכה *Sukkah* which
is supposed to have three walls, the back wall here, the one
that connects the parallel ones, is called the middle wall, okay? So
רבא *Rava* says, if you're going to say פי תקרה יורד וסותם
*pi tikra yored v'sotem*, would you say it even if you needed
it to complete the wall, the back wall? Right? If you didn't
even start by connecting walls, would you say it even there? Okay?
If your real walls were here, would you allow the פי תקרה
*pi tikra*, basically, to close off that middle wall? Is that sort
of clear what the scenario is? No? This case is אביי'ס *Abaye's*
case according to תוספות *Tosafot*, okay? According to תוספות *Tosafot*, אביי'ס *Abaye's*
case is you built, okay, you built two walls. I don't know
if this is clear, maybe we need a square in the middle.
Okay, you built your two walls, right? Okay, you built your real
two walls. At the edge here you have a portico and you're
going to use the portico to פי תקרה *pi tikra* to create
that virtual third wall. That's what אביי *Abaye* says. So רבא *Rava*
says to him, okay, I hear that, I don't agree with it
but I hear it, but what if you built two parallel walls
and you had here some type of a thing? Would you use
that to create, would you say your פי תקרה *pi tikra* here
to fill in the third wall? If you say yes to the
first one, why can't you say yes to that? Because somehow he
feels that that's like absurd because in the first case, you know,
you really have somehow like the real walls really define a type
of an enclosed space. They don't fully enclose the space but they
define, we've had this idea, we've had this idea before: when you
have a corner you've pretty much closed off to some degree that
space. So you want to be more lenient by the third wall,
I get it. But if you have this, you haven't created any
sense of a closed space. Could you create an invisible third wall
there? So that's what he asks him. Let's see his answer, one
minute. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, no, מודינא לך בההיא *modina lach
b'hahi*. Yes, that was a good, that's a good point. That case
I'll concede. דהויא לה כמבוי המפולש *d'hava lah k'maboi hamfulash*. In that
case you're right, the real thing you start with is like basically
like a road, you know, like a road that just has walls
on the side. It's not like a space, it hasn't designated a
space, it's just like walls on the side of a road. There
you can't say פי תקרה *pi tikra*, but when you start with
a designated space and you already are seeing it as a surrounded
space, you can use פי תקרה *pi tikra* there to create the
third wall. Now is this called like a כמבוי המפולש *k'maboi hamfulash*
when they're parallel? Right, when they're parallel. Then it's like, then it's
like a road. It's not like a space. Right. So why wouldn't
the portico roof be like a קורה *kora* and the two walls
be like a מבוי *maboi*? Because a קורה *kora* only works with
a three-wall מבוי *maboi*, not a two-wall מבוי *maboi*. Okay. All right,
so the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: לימא אביי ורבא בפלוגתא דרב
ושמואל קמיפלגי *Leima Abaye v'Rava biplugta d'Rav u'Shmuel kamifligi*. Maybe אביי *Abaye*
and רבא *Rava* debate the debate of רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel*?
דאיתמר *D'itmar*, it was thought, אכסדרה בבקעה *achsadra b'bik'a*. Let's say you
have this portico in a valley. And again, according to תוספות *Tosafot*,
the assumption is you've built two walls. The reason it mentions a
valley is because you otherwise couldn't carry in a valley, it's a
כרמלית *karmelit*. Okay, so you have anyway this portico, again, תוספות *Tosafot*
is reading into this סוגיא *sugya* that it has two walls. רב
אמר מותר לטלטל בכולה *Rav amar mutar letaltel b'kulo*. You can carry
in it, it's a good space. דאמרינן פי תקרה יורד וסותם *d'amrinan
pi tikra yored v'sotem*. ושמואל אמר אין מטלטלין בה אלא בארבע אמות
*u'Shmuel amar ein metaltelin bah ela b'arba amot*. No, it's you can
only carry, right, you know, you're only. Up to four אמות *amot*
and דלא אמרינן פי תקרה יורד וסותם *delo amrinan pi tikreh yored
vesoteam*. Okay, it does not create a רשות היחיד *reshut hayachid*. So
you see this debate, you say פי תקרה *pi tikreh*, the debate
of רבא *Rava* and שמואל *Shmuel*. Isn't that the same debate of
אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says אליבא דשמואל
כולי עלמא לא פליגי *aliba deShmuel kuli alma lo pligi*. According to
שמואל *Shmuel* who says that you don't say פי תקרה יורד וסותם
*pi tikreh yored vesoteam*, clearly then he's like the one who says
you don't say it. He's like רבא *Rava* who doesn't say it
by סוכה *Sukkah* and he's not like אביי *Abaye*. כי פליגי אליבא
דרבא *ki pligi aliba deRava*, the question is whether רבא *Rava* might
concede the point, meaning שמואל *Shmuel* who says it's no good by
שבת *Shabbat* by the carrying scenario would also say it's no good
by סוכה *Sukkah*. That's clear. The question is would רבא *Rava* possibly
change his vote by סוכה *Sukkah*. אביי כרבא *Abaye keRava*, אביי *Abaye*
would say רבא *Rava* goes like me. רבא *Rava* says it works
by שבת *Shabbat*, it's going to work by סוכה *Sukkah*. ורבא אמר
לך *veRava amar lach* and רבא *Rava* would say to you עד
כאן לא אמר רבא התם אלא דמחיצות לאכסדרה הוא דעבידי *ad kan
lo amar Rava hatam ela demchitzot leachsadra hu deavidi*. There רבא *Rava*
concedes it works because there if you have it, if you have
the case about having, because what I didn't tell you is that
that אכסדרה *achsadra* we're talking about is a covered portico. What you
have done in this שבת *Shabbat* case, not the סוכה *Sukkah* case,
is you actually have built a rooftop on top of the אכסדרה
*achsadra*, okay? So it's actually a covered portico, a roofed portico. And
in that case what you're trying to say, and let's say within
that roofed portico you have two kosher walls here. And what you're
trying to say in that case of the roofed portico, and these
are the beams, let this come down and become the third wall.
Okay, so it's a portico yes, but it's like a roofed portico,
okay? So he says you know what, this is better because here
you start off with more real walls. Why do you start off
with more real walls? Because in this case you basically are building,
the walls are being built for the space below. Let's take a
look. He says התם דמחיצות לאכסדרה הוא דעבידי אבל הכא דלאו להכי
עבידי לא *hatam demchitzot leachsadra hu deavidi aval hacha delav lehachi avidi
lo*. But here, right, he says here in this case, actually it's
not these walls, excuse me, in this case the edge of the
roof that is going to be your third wall, right, the edge
of your roof in this case that's going to be your third
wall, people sort of get what I'm drawing? Yes, that's a roof
that is made to serve the אכסדרה *achsadra*. And therefore it might
be more legitimate to use the edge of that roof to create
a wall. In this case, where are you getting the edge of
your roof? You're getting it from outside the אכסדרה *achsadra*, right? You're
getting it from the space over here, that's whatever, right? It's the
rooftop outside the סוכה *Sukkah*. So to use the edge of a
roof that's on outside of the area you care about to be
the beginning of a wall of this space? No. If you want
it to be the beginning of a wall of the space, it
has to be from something that is made to serve the space.
So therefore even though there I say you can use it to
close off the wall, I would not say it when the edge
is on the outside, part of an outside roof, then it's not
relevant to the space in the middle. Now again you'll notice that
our entire גמרא *Gemara* did not mention that you already had two
walls. The simple גמרא *Gemara* made it sound like you could do
it for all the walls, it didn't have any qualifications. But the
reason that pushes תוספות *Tosafot* to say you have two walls, besides
that he has other גמרות *Gemarot* he's dealing with, is because רבא
*Rava* says, well excuse me, אביי *Abaye* says I'll concede the case
when you only have two walls because then it's like a מבוי
המפולש *mavoy hamefulash*. So wait a minute, I thought that's what we're
talking about, that it didn't have any walls and you let it
create all four walls. So what does it mean that you're conceding
the מבוי המפולש *mavoy hamefulash* case? So because of that תוספות *Tosafot*
says we have to assume all of the cases we're talking about
already have two perpendicular walls and then they're only debating using it
for the extra wall. That makes it also a little bit more
understandable what the idea of פי תקרה יורד וסותם *pi tikreh yored
vesoteam* is, that it can complete a third wall once you already
have the space designated. But again that is not explicit in the
גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, יישר כוח *Yasher koach*.